<?xml version="1.0"?>
<learningObject targetFolder="Nottingham" name="Pharmacology" language="en-GB" navigation="Linear" textSize="14" theme="darkblue" displayMode="full screen" editorVersion="3" ic="FileLocation + 'media/Unilogosmall1.png'" stylesheet="" styles="@import url(//fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Sanchez:400,700|Roboto+Slab:400,700|Inconsolata:400,700|Noto+Sans:400);&#10;&#10;body  { &#10;  font-family: &quot;Noto Sans&quot;;&#10;  font-weight:400;&#10;  font-size: 16pt;&#10;  }&#10;  h2 &#10;  { font-family: &quot;Roboto Slab&quot;;&#10;  font-size: 125%;&quot;&#10;  }" resume="true"><text linkID="PG1459931071323" name="Pharmacology revision"><![CDATA[<h2>Learning outcomes</h2>

<p>After participating in this e-learning you will be able to:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Explain the terms Pharmacology, pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics.</li>
	<li>Describe how absorption, distribution, metabolism and excretion affect drug activity</li>
	<li>Describe the general principles of how drugs work in the body</li>
	<li>Explain why some drug interactions occur</li>
</ul>

<h2><i class="fa fa-clock-o"></i> Timing</h2>

<p>This e-learning module should take about 1 hour to complete.</p>

<p>It is important that you are familiar with some basic concepts of pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics. We expect these to be applied in your case study. Also you must answer two out of three short answer questions on general pharmacology in your exam.&nbsp;</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1459931121821" name="Introduction"><![CDATA[<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>Pharmacology is the science that looks at the composition, effects and uses of drugs.</p>

<p>Two very important concepts are pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics.</p>

<p>&nbsp;</p>

<table border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1">
	<tbody>
		<tr>
			<td><a href="asfunction:_level0.engine.rootIcon.pageLink,PG1459934330830">Pharmacokinetics</a></td>
			<td><a href="asfunction:_level0.engine.rootIcon.pageLink,PG1459950685863">Pharmacodynamics</a></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td>concerns how the body processes the drug</td>
			<td>concerns how drugs affect the body</td>
		</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1459934330830" name="Pharmacokinetics"><![CDATA[<h2><span style="font-family: &quot;Open Sans&quot;, sans-serif; background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);">Pharmacokinetics</span></h2>

<p>Pharmacokinetics is the scientific study of how the body processes the drug.</p>

<p>Pharmacokinetics is usually broken down into four stages:</p>

<ol>
	<li>Absorption of the drug</li>
	<li>Distribution of the drug in the different body compartments</li>
	<li>Metabolism of the drug</li>
	<li>Excretion of the drug</li>
</ol>

<p><img alt="Image of the ADME system" height="358" src="FileLocation + 'media/ADME.png'" width="465" /></p>

<p><span style="font-size:12px;">(source:&nbsp;<a href="https://www.eupati.eu/glossary/pharmacokinetics/" target="_blank">https://www.eupati.eu/glossary/pharmacokinetics/</a>)</span></p>
]]></text><tabNavExtra linkID="PG1459935306509" name="ADME"><topic linkID="PG1459935500924" name=""><nestedTab linkID="PG1459936336242" name="Absorption"><nestedPage linkID="PG1459936336251" name="Absorption" text="&lt;p&gt;There are many ways in which drugs may be administrated to enable their absorption.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Following oral administration some of the drug will be absorbed through the stomach lining into the blood&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;However, for most drugs, most absorption will occur in the small intestines. &amp;nbsp;This is because the small intestines are adapted for absorption by having a very extensive surface area.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Blood leaving the stomach and small intestines goes directly to the liver via the hepatic portal vein. Therefore any drug taken orally will go first to the liver before it reaches the general (systemic) circulation. &amp;nbsp;In the liver some of the drug is chemically altered in a process called&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;first pass metabolism&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;First pass metabolism has a significant impact on how much of a drug is available to exert its effects on the body.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Some drugs undergo extensive first pass metabolism.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;This is one reason why some drugs cannot be effectively given by the oral route and absorbed by the gastrointestinal (GI) tract.&amp;nbsp; An example is glyceryl trinitrate which is administered under the tongue (sublingual). If it were swallowed it would be almost entirely broken down during its first passage through the liver.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The sublingual route avoids the first pass metabolism because the drug is directly absorbed into the systemic circulation diffusing into the blood through tissues under the tongue.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Drugs given parenterally (by intravenous, subcutaneous and intramuscular injection) also directly enter the systemic circulation and avoid first pass metabolism in the liver.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Other routes of administration, avoiding first pass metabolism, include the use of transdermal patches, rectal suppositories, and buccal routes (given between gum and cheek). &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1473068377515" name="Other factors affecting absorption" text="&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food and Other Medicines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Food can affect absorption of certain drugs. Patients should be informed if they need to take their drug on an empty stomach. For example, flucloxacillin, an antibiotic should be taken before food as food will affect the amount of drug absorbed. However, the absorption of amoxycillin is unaffected by the presence of food in the stomach and does not need to be taken on an empty stomach.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, two drugs may bind to each other making a larger compound which is not well absorbed. An example is alendronic acid and calcium which are both used in the treatment of osteoporosis. It is usually recommended that patients do not take these at the same time of day. If taken together, the calcium binds to the alendronic acid making a very large molecule&amp;nbsp; which is difficult to absorb.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Controlled release drugs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Controlled release drugs often have &amp;#39;MR&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;SR&amp;#39;&amp;nbsp;or &amp;#39;LA&amp;#39;&amp;nbsp;attached to their names. (These, respectively, stand for modified release, slow release and long-acting). For example, &amp;#39;Morphgesic SR&amp;#39;&amp;nbsp;is a long-acting form of morphine and the SR stands for slow release. These medicines are formulated to be released slowly from the GI tract. As a result, the patient is able to take the tablets less frequently which is often more convenient. Brands are often not interchangeable as they may be formulated differently and have different effects on a patient. In addition, crushing controlled release tablets destroys the slow release mechanism. The patient would receive the whole dose in a non-controlled manner and this may be toxic and the effect of the drug would not be long acting.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enteric coated (e.c.) drugs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Some drugs have a special coating which may delay absorption until a different part of the GI tract is reached. In particular, the coating may help protect the stomach from the drug. A well-known example is Aspirin e.c. The coating prevents aspirin being absorbed in the stomach which helps protect the stomach from irritation. Crushing enteric coated drugs is not advisable as this destroys the coating.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Route of Administration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;As highlighted above, the route of administration will have an impact on first pass metabolism which is important for some drugs and affects how much is absorbed into the systemic circulation. In addition, some drugs, for example, particular penicillins and insulin, are broken down by enzymes in the stomach. This is why these drugs are not administered by the oral route. Sometimes, different routes of administration are used to avoid absorption into the bloodstream altogether in an attempt to reduce side effects. Examples include inhalers, nose drops and eye drops. However, it should be remembered that a small amount of the drug will be absorbed despite this.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/></nestedTab><nestedTab linkID="PG1459935500938" name="Distribution"><nestedPage linkID="PG1459935500942" name="Nested Page Name" text="&lt;p&gt;Distribution describes the process of dispersion or dissemination of drugs throughout the fluids and tissues of the body.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Drugs are not distributed equally in the different fluids and tissues.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;Fat soluble drugs, for example, will concentrate in adipose tissue, and water soluble drugs, in body water.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Some parts of the body are less accessible to drugs than others.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The nervous tissue of the brain is separated from its blood supply by the blood brain barrier.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;A number of drugs cannot cross the blood brain barrier.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;This helps to explain the difference between sedative antihistamines, such as chlorphenamine, and non-sedative ones, such as cetirizine.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;Chlorphenamine causes drowsiness by binding to histamine receptors in the brain.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;By contrast, cetirizine cannot cross the blood brain barrier to bind to histamine receptors in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;When drugs circulate in the bloodstream some of the drug binds to proteins in the plasma; where as some of the drug remains `free&amp;rsquo;, or unbound in the plasma.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The &amp;lsquo;bound&amp;rsquo; drug is effectively inactive as the protein-drug complex is too large to leave the blood capillaries and enter the tissue fluid surrounding the body cells.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The &amp;lsquo;free&amp;rsquo; drug is small enough to pass through the capillary wall and enter the tissue fluid to exert its effect on the cells.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Things that affect protein binding, such as older age or other drugs, may affect the amount of drug available to the tissues.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/></nestedTab><nestedTab linkID="PG1459936349527" name="Metabolism"><nestedPage linkID="PG1459936349531" name="Basics" text="&lt;p&gt;Metabolism comes from a Greek word that means &amp;ldquo;to change&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;265&quot; src=&quot;FileLocation + 'media/liver.jpeg'&quot; style=&quot;float:left&quot; width=&quot;283&quot; /&gt;Metabolism of drugs occurs mainly in the liver.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;We often think of the liver as breaking drugs down and making them inactive but this is too simplistic.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Metabolism can reduce activity or create other active metabolites. In some cases metabolism activates drugs.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of metabolism is to make the drug into something more water soluble so that it can be excreted from the body by the kidneys.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1459936547035" name="Codeine metabolism" text="&lt;p&gt;The Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency (MHRA) issued a safety warning about codeine in 2013.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;They stated that codeine should only be used for acute, moderate pain in children over 12 years and only if other pain killers (analgesics) did not work. This followed cases of children receiving codeine after surgery who developed respiratory depression.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Respiratory depression can be a side effect of morphine.&amp;nbsp; Codeine is a pro-drug, which means it is metabolised in the liver to morphine and this is what is responsible for the analgesia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;A pro-drug is an inactive precursor which is converted to an active drug by metabolism. It is believed that the affected children were rapid metabolisers of codeine. As a result, these children produced unexpectedly high levels of morphine resulting in respiratory depression.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Conversely, some patients are slow metabolisers and benefit little from codeine. This is due to their slow rate of metabolism of codeine into morphine.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;There are two phases of metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1459936571930" name="Phase 1 metabolism" text="&lt;p&gt;This is mainly carried out by a large family of enzymes in the liver called cytochrome P450 enzymes which oxidise drugs.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;There are different kinds of these enzymes and some are quite specific for different drugs. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;A number of drugs can bind to cytochrome P450 enzymes to increase their activity. This is enzyme induction.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;By contrast other drugs bind to the enzymes and reduce their activity (enzyme inhibition). This is a common way for drugs to drug interactions to occur.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1459938304610" name="Activity" text="&lt;p&gt;Smoking is an enzyme inducer in that it speeds up the enzymes that usually metabolise the antipsychotic drug olanzapine.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;What might happen to a smoker on olanzapine who stops smoking?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;div id=&quot;hiddenText&quot;&gt;A smoker might need to be on a higher dose of olanzapine as the enzymes that metabolise olanzapine will be speeded up. &amp;nbsp; If the patient stops smoking the enzymes slow back down again. &amp;nbsp; This would mean olanzapine levels rise. This could lead to toxicity or increased side effects.&#10;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;You would want to advise the patient of this and that their dose of olanzapine may need to be reduced when they have stopped smoking&lt;/div&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot; onclick=&quot;$('#hiddenText').show(); return false;&quot;&gt;Click here to reveal the answer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1459936588697" name="Phase 2 metabolism" text="&lt;p&gt;In phase 2 metabolism, a large ionised molecule is added to the drug. This acts to increase the water solubility of the drug.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;In general, drugs undergo phase 1 and then phase 2 metabolism. However, some drugs will only undergo phase 1 and some will undergo only phase 2. A drug might also be metabolised by different pathways resulting in many different&amp;nbsp;metabolites. Factors that affect the function of the liver, such as disease and aging, can affect how much of a drug is metabolised. As we have shown in the evidence summary, some people metabolise things more quickly than others. This is probably reflects differences in their genetic make-up.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The liver is the main site of drug metabolism but drugs may also be metabolised in the GI tract, the plasma and the lungs.&amp;nbsp; Morphine, for example, is metabolised mainly in the liver but also in the mucosal cells of the small intestine.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/></nestedTab><nestedTab linkID="PG1459936359632" name="Excretion (elimination)"><nestedPage linkID="PG1459936359639" name="Nested Page Name" text="&lt;p&gt;Excretion (elimination) refers to the removal of waste products from the body.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;FileLocation + 'media/kidney.jpg'&quot; style=&quot;float:left&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;The kidney is the main organ involved in drug excretion.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;If you could examine the urine of a patient taking drugs, you would find water-soluble drugs and metabolites.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Drugs may also be excreted in bile, tears, sweat and breath. In fact any bodily fluid can contain drugs and their metabolites.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Factors that affect kidney function, such as kidney disease and aging will affect how efficiently the body excretes s drugs.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/></nestedTab></topic></tabNavExtra><tabNav linkID="PG1459942075328" name="Other important pharmacokinetic concepts" text="" panelWidth="Full"><nestedPage linkID="PG1459942099620" name="Bioavailablity" text="&lt;p&gt;Bioavailability is the proportion of drug that enters the circulation after a dose is administered.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;For intravenous (IV) drugs, it can be assumed to be 100% as the drug is delivered directly into the blood circulation.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;For oral drugs it can be considerably less.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The losses occur in numerous ways. Some of the tablet may not be absorbed from GI tract and some may be lost during first pass metabolism before reaching systemic circulation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;It is often expressed as a percentage.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;For example the bioavailability of the opioid pain killer Oxycodone is 60-87% which means only 60-87% of the orally administered dose reaches the systemic circulation.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" align="Top"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1459942124139" name="Case study" text="&lt;p&gt;Michael is receiving palliative care. His pain is currently controlled using morphine MST continus tablets 60mg twice a day.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;He is finding it increasingly difficult to swallow and a subcutaneous infusion has been suggested as an alternative route of administration.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The equivalent subcutaneous dose of morphine is half the oral dose (British National Formulary (BNF) Palliative Care Guidance) that is 60mg over 24 hours. This is because the bioavailability of oral morphine is much less than morphine given by injection. This difference is largely due to the first pass metabolism of morphine when administered orally.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the bioavailability of different brands and formulations can be different. For example, the bioavailability of Lanoxin (Digoxin) elixir is 75% compared to 63% for Lanoxin tablets. For many drugs this does not matter clinically but, in cases where the drug has a narrow therapeutic index or range, it can be important.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" align="Top"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1459942139251" name="Narrow therapeutic index or range" text="&lt;p&gt;This describes the difference between the blood levels that need to be reached for a drug to be effective, and the level above which the drug is toxic.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;For many drugs, this range is very wide, for example with paracetamol most adult patients need a dose of 1g to relieve their pain.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;For drugs with a narrow therapeutic range, for example, digoxin, gentamycin, vancomycin and lithium, small differences in dose or blood concentration may lead to therapeutic failures or adverse drug reactions.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;It is often necessary to adjust the dose according to measurement of the actual blood level achieved in the person taking it.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Changes in the brand or formulation can result in toxic or sub therapeutic levels in the blood because of differences in bioavailability&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;186&quot; src=&quot;FileLocation + 'media/plasm-drug-conc.png'&quot; width=&quot;323&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" align="Top"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1459942249094" name="Plasma half-life" text="&lt;p&gt;The plasma half-life of a drug is the time it takes for the concentration of the drug in the plasma to reduce by one half. It is a constant for any given drug, although a range is often given as some people metabolise and excrete drugs faster than others.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;It is a useful measure at it can help you to work out how long drugs last in the body. It can take 4 to 5 half-lives for a drug to be excreted.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#000080;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:16px;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:verdana,geneva,sans-serif;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;207&quot; src=&quot;FileLocation + 'media/concentrations.gif'&quot; width=&quot;308&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The red line of the graph above is what happens to a single dose. From the graph we can see that the half- life is 6 hours.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The other lines show what happens after repeated administration.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;It takes 4 to 5 half lifes for a drug to reach steady state. At steady state the amount leaving the circulation equals that entering the circulation&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" align="Top"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1459950141467" name="Activity" text="&lt;p&gt;One of your patients, Linda, is on Risperidone 4mg at night for schizophrenia.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;You stopped the drug as she was experiences tremors.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;She asks you how long it will take for the drug to `get out of her system&amp;rsquo;? &amp;nbsp;&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Risperidone has an active metabolite with a half-life of 24 hours.&amp;nbsp;&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;div id=&quot;hiddenText&quot;&gt;It can take 4 to 5 half-lives for a drug to be excreted. . &amp;nbsp; You can tell Linda that it might take 4 or 5 days (4-5 x 24 hours) for the risperidone to be out of her system but the side effects should get better every day, as every day the remaining drug is broken down and excreted.&#10;&lt;/div&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot; onclick=&quot;$('#hiddenText').show(); return false;&quot;&gt;Click here to reveal the answer&lt;/a&gt;&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" align="Top"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1459950459093" name="Peak plasma concentrations" text="&lt;p&gt;The timing of the peak plasma concentration gives useful information about when drug levels are at their highest in a patient&amp;rsquo;s blood.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Some side effects tend to be most problematic at this time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" align="Top"/></tabNav><text linkID="PG1459950685863" name="Pharmacodynamics"><![CDATA[<h2><span style="font-family: &quot;Open Sans&quot;, sans-serif; background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);">Pharmacodynamics</span></h2>

<p>Pharmacodynamics, sometimes described as `what drugs do to the body&rsquo;, is defined as the study of the biochemical and physiological effects of drugs on the body. This includes the mechanism of drug action, and the side effects they cause.</p>

<p>In order for a drug to exert an effect, it must first come into contact with, and bind to, the cells of the body it is acting upon.</p>

<p>Different drug molecules have different shapes and will only bind to certain proteins in the body.</p>

<p>Have you have ever had a patient ask you how a drug knows where to go?</p>

<p>For example, &quot;how does paracetamol know to go to the head and stop a headache?&rsquo;&quot;</p>

<p>The drug does not know&nbsp;but will bind to certain binding sites the body.</p>

<p>Most of these binding sites are proteins. There are many different proteins in the body, all with different shapes.</p>

<p>The following are common binding sites for drugs: &nbsp;receptors, enzymes and carrier molecules.</p>
]]></text><tabNav linkID="PG1459951059193" name="Drugs acting at receptors" text="&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &amp;quot;Open Sans&amp;quot;, sans-serif; background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);&quot;&gt;Drugs acting at receptors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Many drug receptors are protein molecules on the surface of a cell, signalling molecules bind to these receptors to cause a response in the cell.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;307&quot; src=&quot;FileLocation + 'media/agonists.png'&quot; width=&quot;395&quot; /&gt;&#10;&lt;figcaption&gt;Image source: http://membranereceptors.com/&lt;/figcaption&gt;&#10;&lt;/figure&gt;&#10;" panelWidth="Medium"><nestedPage linkID="PG1459951225981" name="agonist" text="&lt;p&gt;The general name for a chemical that binds to a receptor and activates it to produce a response is an agonist.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Many drugs acting at receptors are agonists.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;For example, adrenaline is an agonist. It binds to beta receptors on heart muscle cells to set off a chain of events which leads to the heart beating faster and more forcefully.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" align="Top"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1459951270387" name="antagonist" text="&lt;p&gt;While an agonist causes a response an antagonist binds to the receptor but does not cause a response.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Antagonists block the receptor so that an agonist cannot exert its effect.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;An example of an antagonist is propranolol, a beta blocker. Propranolol attaches to the beta receptors on the heart muscle cells preventing adrenaline binding. This consequently prevents the action of adrenaline. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" align="Top"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1459951326083" name="partial agonists" text="&lt;p&gt;Partial agonists bind to receptors to cause a response but the response is less than the maximum possible.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The opioid buprenorphine is an example of a partial agonist.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;This makes it a useful drug in the treatment of opioid dependence, where the opioid agonist heroin (also known as diamorphine) is replaced by another agonist, in this case buprenorphine, to prevent withdrawal symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;We shall come across many drugs acting as agonists and antagonists in the following chapters.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" align="Top"/></tabNav><text linkID="PG1460018561928" name="Drugs acting on enzymes"><![CDATA[<h2><span style="font-family: &quot;Open Sans&quot;, sans-serif; background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);">Drugs acting on enzymes</span></h2>

<p>Enzymes are chemicals (usually proteins) that speed up the chemical reactions and keep cells functioning.</p>

<p>Drugs acting as enzyme inhibitors, bind to the enzyme and decrease its activity.</p>

<p>An example of an enzyme inhibitor is the non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID), ibuprofen. Ibuprofen binds to and inhibits enzymes called cyclooxygenases (COXs). COXs are enzymes which are needed to make a group of inflammatory molecules called prostaglandins. Prostaglandins cause pain and fever.</p>

<p>Ibuprofen inhibits the COXs and reduces the amount of prostaglandins synthesised. Pain and fever are reduced as a result.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1460018631224" name="Drugs acting on transporters"><![CDATA[<h2><span style="font-family: &quot;Open Sans&quot;, sans-serif; background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);">Drugs acting on transporters</span></h2>

<p>Transporter&nbsp;proteins are located in the cell membrane.</p>

<p>Their function is to transport substances across the cell membrane.</p>

<p>A good example of a drug&nbsp;acting on transporter proteins are the type of antidepressant drug called Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors (SSRIs). Examples of SSRIs include fluoxetine and citalopram.</p>

<p><img alt="" height="281" src="FileLocation + 'media/SSRI.png'" style="float:left" width="365" /></p>

<p>Between nerve cells there is a gap called a synapse.</p>

<p>In order for a message to be carried from one cell to another a chemical, called a neurotransmitter is needed.&nbsp;</p>

<p>Serotonin is a type of neurotransmitter.</p>

<p>Antidepressant drugs act to increase the level of neurotransmitters in the synapse. SSRIs do this by preventing the reuptake of serotonin from the synapse, this means more serotonin is available for longer to stimulate serotonin receptors on the nerve cell the other side of the synapse.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>

<p>(image source:&nbsp;<a href="https://web.stanford.edu/group/hopes/cgi-bin/hopes_test/ssris/" target="_blank">https://web.stanford.edu/group/hopes/cgi-bin/hopes_test/ssris/</a>)</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1460365205724" name="Further reading"><![CDATA[<h2><span style="font-family: &quot;Open Sans&quot;, sans-serif; background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);">Further reading</span></h2>

<p>British National Formulary (BNF) 70 (2015) Pharm Press, London.The essential practical, evidence-based information for health care professionals who prescribe, dispense and administer medicines</p>

<p>Simonsen, T, Aarbakke, J, Kay, I, Coleman, I, Sinnott, P, and Lysaa, R. (2006). Illustrated pharmacology for nurses. Hodder Arnold. London, UK.</p>

<p>Useful websites</p>

<p><a href="http://www.medicines.org.uk/" target="_blank">www.medicines.org.uk</a> The electronic Medicines Compendium (eMC) contains information about medicines licensed for use in the UK. Summaries of product characteristics (SPC) and patient information leaflets (PILs) are available.</p>
]]></text></learningObject>
